Clear.
- "Stand down. Exercise complete."
- Damn. We'll get you guys next time.
- We won?
- Yes.
- F.B.I.'s having a good showing this year.
- Thank you.
- Colonel?
- Yes?
I believe you have
something for me.
- Week's not over yet.
- Bring it on.
This idea you have about quitting
were you ever gonna bring it up again?
Well, it's just a thought.
For the record, I enjoy what we do.
Well, you might enjoy Paris
or learning pedal steel guitar.
- Pedal steel guitar?
- The world is infinite in its possibilities.
It's not gonna be as easy
to walk away as you think.
Why do you say that?
You enjoy the mental stimulation
far more than you let on.
- Agent Lisbon.
- Colonel Raymond.
We met at a seminar...
"Tactical Solutions to Urban Terrorism."
Colonel Raymond,
this is Patrick Jane.
He works as a consultant
with the team.
That was some fine work back there
clearing those rooms just now.
If you ever decide you're
tired of the Bureau
- I can have a space for you.
- That's flattering. Thank you.
Now if you'll excuse me
I need to talk to a couple men
about ambush tactics.
Yeah.
Did... did you ever have
a fling with that guy?
- What?
- Of course not. Sorry.
It's just strange.
Strange that I didn't have
a fling with Colonel Raymond?
Yeah, there's something
going on there.
- You don't know?
- Know what?
His wife was murdered
eight months ago.
- Really?
- It was all over the news.
Did they catch anyone?
Yeah, they arrested somebody right after.
I need a shower.
Eight months ago, huh?
The murder of Colonel Raymond's
wife is closed.
So you're not interested
in hearing my theory?
Okay. What's your theory?
Well, I don't have one yet
but that's why we need to look into it.
Excuse me. Sorry.
Cho needs you to sign this.
So you don't have anything?
No. At this point,
I'm just curious.
Curiosity killed the cat.
Also cured polio.
Aaron Raymond is not just
a colonel in the Marines.
He's a decorated war hero.
And they've already arrested
a man for the murder.
So what makes you think that man
didn't commit the crime?
Well, I'm not sure that he didn't.
I'm just saying, there is...
there is something off about
this Colonel Raymond.
Lisbon, what do you think?
If Jane says it's worth looking into
then it's worth looking into.
You know to trust his instincts.
No interrogations, no searches.
If you wanna talk to anyone,
use a cover story.
A civil rights case for the man
who was arrested maybe.
Raymond is not to learn
that we are looking into this.
Anyone finds out
that we're investigating here
it's over.
Deal.
Pound it.
Thank you, sir.
- You want a coffee or something?
- I'm good, thanks.
Yeah, it sucks anyway.
I gotta tell you
I'm not thrilled to have my work
checked by the F.B.I.
I'm not thrilled to be here.
Mind if I ask why?
The man you charged with the crime
Zach Jefferson, has taken preliminary steps
to file a civil rights violation
against your department.
- Civil rights violation? For what?
- You tell me.
We caught your man Jefferson
in Nicole Raymond's car
one day after
she was murdered.
The victim's wallet was in the car
as well as jewelry stolen from the house.
Murder scene had signs of a break-in.
Slam dunk.
You look at any other suspects?
The husband, maybe?
Yeah, yeah, 9 times out of 10,
husband did it.
- This is time number 10.
- How can you be so sure?
Check this out.
Aaron Raymond's car
was in the shop that day.
They took Nicole's car.
She dropped him off at work.
They got caught
in a red light camera.
M.E. says based on liver temp
Nicole Raymond was killed
no earlier than 10:00 a.m.
Aaron Raymond got to work
that day at 9:00.
We got confirmation
he never left.
You wanna tell me
how he could be the killer?
What's this about?
We wanted to talk to you
about Nicole Raymond's death.
Why?
Zach, the F.B.I. assures me
this is an off-the-record chat.
They just wanna hear our side.
Yeah, right.
Why don't you tell us
what you were doing
before you were arrested?
I was living in a halfway house.
All right? Bagging groceries.
Then I moved in with a friend...
you know, couch surfing.
He got a new girlfriend, she didn't like me
so I had to move out.
You were homeless.
Short-term.
I mean, yeah, I could have moved
back into the halfway house
but them people
be on your case, and...
What were you doing
the day of the arrest?
Look, I found the car. All right?
Keys in it and everything.
Is it really stealing if someone
just leaves something like that?
You've been arrested three times.
Shoplifting, possession.
So?
It's not crazy to think you might try
robbing somebody's house.
Let's just cut right to it.
Did you kill Nicole Raymond?
Man, I never killed anybody.
What?
Well, what do you think?
- You believe him?
- Agents.
It looks bad, but Zach
didn't do this.
He's probably gonna get
the needle.
Obviously, if there's anything
you can do, it'd be appreciated.
If he's telling the truth
then Raymond killed his wife
and then dumped the car
in a bad neighborhood
just hoping somebody
would steal it.
Well, that's not outside
the realm of possibility.
Every good plan needs
a little bit of luck.
We should go visit
the crime scene.
Hi, Judy.
My girlfriend and I
are out house hunting
and, uh, we saw a lovely
place on Roosevelt.
Wondering if we could take
a little peek inside.
Yeah, we're out front.
See you soon. Bye.
- On her way.
- Nice.
As you can see, this house
is move-in ready.
There's a lot to love
about this place
but if you ask me, this cozy living area
is a real dream.
- How long has it been on the market?
- A couple months.
Rally? At this price?
What's the catch?
Wait until you
see the master bath.
Is there something
you're not telling us, Judy?
Out with it.
Well, uh, there was
a death here.
A murder.
Shouldn't you have told us
that to begin with?
- Isn't there a law about that?
- Yeah.
I don't know if it's
my responsibility...
You know, I think we're gonna
have to talk about this
if you don't mind, privately.
Oh. Sure. Well, I have some calls to make
so I'll be out in my car.
Just take your time.
Window was open,
screen outside.
The cops think that's how
Jefferson broke into the house.
Through here?
Okay.
Lisbon, take a look at this.
Hi!
Maybe there wasn't
anybody there that day.
Maybe.
What was the weather like
day of the murder?
Crime report says it was...
mid 70s, clear skies.
Perfect day for the park.
Which begs a question.
Why would you break in
through that window
when you can break in
around the side through there
hidden from the street?
Now the body was found here
with a half-finished crossword
puzzle and a pen.
So we can assume
that she was sitting... there.
- She would have heard him.
- Yes, she would have heard him.
But if Raymond was the killer...
Very easy to push that screen
out from the inside.
Yeah, but the time of death,
he couldn't have done it.
Sure. That's... That's calculated
from body temperature, right?
Liver temperature, yes.
She had a fan pointed right at her
like it was really hot.
But it was Mid 70s.
Perfect day, fan...
- You ever cook a roast?
- Of course.
Yeah. Sorry.
My aunt used to do it this way...
she turned the oven way up high.
You heat it, you put the roast in
and then you turn it off.
So maybe...
He turns the thermostat
all the way up.
Tells her it's broken.
And then he turns the thermostat off
after he kills her.
The room and Nicole
cool off slower
making it seem like she died
later than she actually did.
Exactly.
What about the fan?
"He turned off both the fan
and the thermostat."
"And then he leaves."
Then he leaves.
The front door.
- Looks like it was wiped down.
- For prints.
Raymond doesn't have to
worry about prints.
- It's his house.
- Well, maybe he got blood on it.
No. He's too meticulous.
You're right. He wouldn't leave
that mistake in the first place.
Maybe he was wiping off
somebody else's prints.
- Okay. Okay.
- A woman.
It had to have been a woman.
There was a woman with him in the car
for the red light photograph.
- After Nicole was already dead.
- Yes.
We need to find out who
that woman was in the car.
It gives him motive.
How do we find her?
Well, I think it's time
I paid our pal Raymond a visit
have a little talk about
"Tactical Solutions to Urban Terrorism."
- I told you.
- Told me what?
You can't quit.
You're having too much fun.
Judy.
I'm sorry. I think we're gonna
have to pass on this one.
- Not enough closet space.
- You heard the woman.
"Yes?"
Colonel Raymond.
The F.B.I. consultant, right?
You here for the seminar?
Oh, that's no way to learn.
I prefer one-on-one.
That's why I'm here.
You need some advice?
Oh, given the way your boys performed
in that game yesterday, I thought
you might be asking
for advice yourself.
Your agents got lucky.
Now I try to teach my men not to
let the other side get lucky like that.
Yeah, I could hear your men
whispering their plans back and forth.
Let me tell you something
about plans, Colonel.
They get in the way of instincts.
You don't believe in battle plans?
Well, wasn't it Napoleon that once said
"No plan survives the first shot"?
- A student of combat.
- More of people.
Well, Napoleon did all right in his day
but I'd tell him the secret to that is
never let your opponent
fire that first shot.
That's a little unsporting.
Sports are make-believe,
Mr. Jane. War is real.
Maybe the only real thing
we have left.
That's the stupidest thing
I've ever heard.
You're trying to provoke me.
Why?
To see how you react.
Did you learn something?
Yeah.
I think I did.
Thanks for your time.
It's called a rungu.
It's a Masai warrior war club.
It's normal decor for a soldier.
Yes, but the African art
doesn't have any analog
in the crime scene photos.
Excuse me?
Well, everything else
in the office...
the books, the photos,
the patriotic art...
all had something similar
in the house
the way it was decorated
the day of the murder.
- But there was no African art.
- No.
So... maybe he had a girlfriend
and maybe she had an interest
in African art.
Should we tail him?
No, he's a soldier in military intelligence.
He can spot a tail.
Most affairs are with people that you meet
in your everyday life.
They're familiar.
Workplace.
So she's a marine.
Well, the Wynn complex has over
a thousand government employees
everything from the N.S.A.
to the post office.
How do we narrow that down?
We need to send someone back
into the Wynn complex
preferably someone
that hasn't been involved
in the training exercises.
That leaves out Lisbon, yourself.
I was there Tuesday
for military training.
Okay. Could you do me a favor?
Next time Wylie steals a glance at you,
could you wave him in?
What?
Stop it.
Hey, I'm from I.T.
- What can I help you with?
- Wrong office.
All right. Thanks.
Hey. From I.T.
Hi, I'm here from I.T.
Thank you.
Come in.
Hey. I'm from I.T.
Is this about Candy Pilots?
'Cause I know you're not supposed to
download games.
I just... I have a lot of down time.
What? No.
Okay then. What's up?
I'm here to check
your data stacks.
What's a data stack?
- I asked, what's a data stack?
- Oh, right.
Here, I'll show you.
Denise Sparks, 36.
She works as an information analyst
for the D.O.D.
Could she and Raymond
have crossed paths?
She does a weekly antiterrorism briefing
for top brass, including Raymond.
Love springs up
in the unlikeliest of places.
I found her Facebook page.
She's got lots of photos
of her in Africa.
No pictures of her
and a boyfriend.
Uh, could you put her
next to the red light photo?
That could be her.
Could you engineer a meeting?
Get a read on her,
see if she's our girl?
- Yeah.
- Well, why should I have all the fun?
- What was she like?
- I don't know. She seemed nice.
We're just looking
for impressions.
"She's very clean,
well put together."
"Manicured hands."
"But she chewed the skin
around her nails."
What did she order?
"Coffee, black.
Paid cash."
"She waited until the woman
behind the counter"
"could see her put her tip
in the tip jar."
Interesting. I wonder if I do that.
Four sugars.
It was a lot.
Yeah, that is a lot.
So you talked to her.
- You said, "I like your bag."
- "How'd you know that?"
"Because that's what you think
other women talk about."
Well, it worked. We talked.
Tell me about her.
I don't know. She's reserved.
"It's the kind of quiet where maybe she
could be a raging bitch, or she's just shy."
"And what's your verdict?"
You want me to say if she's a killer
based on spending one minute with her?
Sure.
Well, how do I do that?
Well, your brain's already
processed all the information.
You just have to listen to it.
So, on the count of three,
you're gonna say "yes" or "no."
- 1... 2...
- The answer is yes. I don't need 3.
She could have done it.
Everything about her it just seemed
like she was wearing a mask.
Okay then.
Very nice, Agent Lisbon.
Thank you.
So the theory is
Denise helped Raymond kill his wife
and then she dressed up like him?
Well, Jane thinks they ran
the red light on purpose.
The photograph would give
Raymond an airtight alibi.
Can I see that?
Yeah.
Don't do it fast.
Do it right.
We have nothing
approaching hard evidence.
Yeah, well, that's
where you come in.
This is where the red light
photo was taken.
They dumped the car here,
where Jefferson found it.
It's walking distance
to the Wynn complex.
They walked there
right after the murder?
It's the only way the timing works.
Denise...
Had to change back into
her work clothes at some point.
- Notice she's not driving.
- So?
Jane's theory is she changed
clothes in the car.
Then she had to throw them away.
Maybe she threw them
out the car window.
Or she pulled over and threw it
away in a dumpster.
I don't think they risk
getting out of the car.
Even if Jane's theory is right
that's at least 5 miles.
- I can't search 5 miles.
- You won't have to.
Go.
Don't rush.
I, I mean, she wouldn't have rushed.
And we want it to time out right.
Sure.
Done.
Okay, so now what?
We grid search.
Divide the side of the street
into 1-foot squares.
Examine every square carefully.
That's gonna take
a long time.
Keep talking, it'll take even longer.
You heard north, I head south.
Hello?
Hello?!
F.B.I. anyone home?
Vega?
I think I've got something.
Agent Lisbon.
May I have a moment of your time?
- Sure. Have a seat.
- Someplace private.
How can I help you?
I just wanted to know
if you think I murdered my wife.
Well, I certainly
think you did. Hi.
Then arrest me.
That's what I thought.
- What's going on here?
- Just got ambushed.
A Detective Rios called me.
He wanted to know if the F.B.I.
had been touch
about a civil rights case.
Do you know anything
about this little investigation?
Well, that's a damn shame.
I liked you.
The investigation ends now.
Thank you.
You seem like a smart person.
Know when you've
overplayed your hand.
My office. Now.
We've got the fabric
at the lab right now, rush job.
If it holds either Denise
or Raymond's D.N.A.
or some of Nicole's blood
I think we've got a real shot at this.
A piece of fabric
from a homeless encampment.
Even if the lab turns up anything
you don't have it.
Now I think that you and Jane
did some nice work
but not enough
to reopen the case.
No prosecutor is gonna go after this man
without having solid evidence.
We've gotten as close as we can
working off the books.
Maybe if you put us
in front of a judge.
Anything short of a confession
and they will never reopen the case.
I'm sorry. It's over.
When we get the results from the lab
we'll just try again.
Anything short of a confession.
What?
Let's go for the confession.
- Hey.
- What are you doing here?
- Well, I got your message.
- I didn't send you a message.
Morning. Uh, could you
have a seat, please?
I'm sorry. Patrick Jane,
Teresa Lisbon.
He didn't tell you
we're investigating you?
This is outrageous.
- I'm calling Abbott.
- Oh, feel free.
That's embarrassing.
Guess I picked up the wrong phone.
You'll have to talk to him later.
Then I want my lawyer here.
You'll be talking
to your lawyer soon enough.
We'll get to that.
You wanna tell me
what's going on?
Yes. In this briefcase,
I have a report from the crime lab.
I sent something in
to be tested.
When we open it, we will know
if it implicates
one of you, or both of you.
If one of you confesses before
I open the briefcase
we'll cut you a deal.
After the briefcase is open
no deals for anyone.
I'm gonna open the briefcase
in five minutes.
And that five minutes...
Starts now.
You don't have anything on us.
Well, we'll soon see,
won't we?
So exciting.
- I'm walking out of here.
- Go.
- We should go.
- You should stay.
I don't think you understand
how much he hasn't told you.
We'll sit here for five minutes
let them open the briefcase
see that they don't have anything on us
and then we walk out of here.
- Aaron...
- Not a word.
- Definitely in a relationship.
- Yep.
That's not a crime.
- There's no need...
- No... I love him.
- I love you.
- I love you, too
but now's not the time.
- But you know that I would never...
- Of course.
And you know.
If either of you was smart,
this game would be over by now.
Do you ever lay awake at night
wondering what's gonna happen
to you when he gets tired of you
just like he got tired of Nicole?
Colonel, you've carried out
battle plans before.
How hard could
the perfect murder be?
- You did a nice job.
- Very nice. One little mistake.
Was it the thermostat?
Or the wig.
Or was it the clothes
you threw out the window
- on... where was it? 23rd Street.
- 23rd Street.
Time waits for no man...
Or woman.
- This is...
- Stop talking.
- But, Aaron...
- Woman, I'm telling you.
What is it you wanna say?
- "Aaron..."
- Don't be stupid!
All right, I'll talk.
- We did it.
- No, you did it!
No, he's the one who did it!
I didn't do it! He did it!
You...
Nicole said she'd fight the divorce.
She'd take the house, everything.
What right did she have?
Up until the moment she did it
I didn't think it would happen.
He said it would be one bad day
and then a lifetime of happiness.
He told me that she would drag us
both through the mud
that I'd be labeled
a home wrecker.
She said it'd be quick.
She was a different person.
He let me in.
It was so hot.
And when he let me in,
he got the knife off the rack.
He smiled when he did it.
He st...
he stabbed her.
He said something
under his breath when...
"when he killed her."
I don't know what.
"He stabbed her."
"I just...
just stood there..."
"and watched."
She wasn't the same person.
Call Zach Jefferson's attorney.
Give her the good news.
Got it.
Jane, which one was it?
What do you mean?
Who stabbed Nicole?
Was it Raymond or Denise?
- I don't know.
- You don't know?
No. Does it matter?
Well, what...
Well, what's in that?
Did you really get evidence
on one of them?
- Which one was it?
- Good night.
Are you at all curious
about what's in that briefcase?
Haven't stopped thinking
about it for a second.
Should we take a look?
- Ah, I don't know.
- Come on, let's take a look.
Okay.
Meow!
Sorry?
- Okay. Admit it.
- Admit what?
You enjoyed yourself.
You love this job as much as I do.
Well, I love eggs,
but that doesn't mean
I wanna eat nothing but omelets
for the rest of my life.
Fair enough.
What was the alternative?
Pork chops, Cole slaw,
French fries.
What's the alternative for us?
You talk about quitting,
but what are we gonna do?
- What's the plan?
- Well, I don't have one as yet.
Well, that's a problem, isn't it?
Well, if we wait for a plan,
we might never leave.
Maybe we just need to quit
and sit still for a while.
Let life happen.
Let a plan take seed.
Wait for plan seeds to grow?
We'd drive each other crazy.
Maybe. Maybe not.
Maybe we'd be very happy.
- Won't know until we try.
- Aren't you happy now?
Well, I am happy
for the first time
in you know how long,
but I'm scared.
Jane, one of us could get
run over by a bus tomorrow.
Not if we're on a beach
in Polynesia.
Buses can't go on sand.
- You could get eaten by a shark.
- Not if you don't go in the water.
That sounds pretty boring
and wussy, don't you think?
Yeah, they have palm trees
and hammocks and cocktails
and sunsets, pineapples...
And endless boredom, sunburn,
bugs the size of helicopters.
- I've been on vacation.
- Now you're just being negative.
It was an example
of how we could avoid buses.
But we could do
anything we want.
We could learn to sail, buy
a boat, sail around the world.
Yeah, right.
Wh-What? I always wanted to do that.
A lot of people do it.
I mean, we could do it.
As in whales and storms
and pirates? Scurvy?
And besides, I get seasick.
- You do?
- Yeah.
- How badly?
- Pretty bad.
Maybe you'd get over that.
We are not
sailing around the world.
All right.
Beekeeping?
Who doesn't like honey?
Oh, you just come up with
the best ideas. Beekeeping?
Well, I think you'd look very cute
in one of those little beekeeping suits.
How is that romantic?
You...
Yeah?